A Guide to the Southern Student Organizing Committee Additional Papers 1963-1979
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Southern Student Organizing Committee Additional Papers 1963-1979
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11192-e
This collection contains ca. 500 items (4 Hollinger boxes and 3 oversize boxes, ca. 1.5 linear feet).
This collection consists of additional papers of the Southern Student Organizing Committee, 1963-1979.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library on October 2, 1996, by Steve Wise of Atlanta, Georgia.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of additional papers of the Southern Student Organizing Committee, ca. 1963-1979, and undated, collected by Steve Wise, including miscellaneous publications; some by a variety of other organizations. Materials include printed items, memoranda, mimeographed publications, newspapers, articles, typed manuscripts, news clippings, order blanks for literature, agendas, conference materials, and form letters concerning student events.
Arrangement
The publications have been arranged alphabetically according to the name of the organization responsible for the material or its subject. A full listing of each subject or publication can be found in the box listing under its folder heading.
Contents List
- A-B (general) 1963-1968 (Box 1)
  including: The Activist(1966); AFL-CIO American Federationist reprints re corporate profits and organizing; the Agrarian Work Project; U.S. Dept. of Agriculture economic reports No. 26 & 28; The American Student(1966); "A Just Family Income Policy" by Americans for Democratic Action; articles about Appalachia and its problems; articles about "Black Power"; "Bolivia: Another Vietnam?"; "The Nomination of Farris Bryant: Some Facts and Analysis
- C (general) 1965-1977 (Box 1)
  including: Campus Progressive(1966 April 22); human rights in Chile (1977); "Toward the New City"; College Young Democratic Clubs of America by-laws, platform, and manual; Committee For World Development and World Disarmament "The Case for Development"; Community Foundation Memorandum #1; Connections Supplement; "Article on Consumer Co-ops written for Radicals in the Professions" by Richard Rothstein"; Conversion Report (1964); articles on cybernation by Dale Richard Caldwell and Robert Theobald
- Conference on Radical Vocations in the White Community [1968?] Feb (Box 1)
- D-J (general) 1964-1967 (Box 1)
  including: Democratic ACTION(1966 Sep); form letter inviting people to attend a conference for friends of the "democratic left"; "How to Expose & Fight the Democratic Party in Your Community by Lee Webb; Dimensions Discussion Journal of the W.E.B. Dubois Clubs (1966); "DOW All Over" by Bob Schwartz; Duke Employees Local 77; 49th Ward Committee for Independent Political Action (1966); "The Genesis of the Great Society" by William E. Leuchtenberg; GROW A New Movement in the White South by Robert Analavage; paper on "Free Public Higher Education"; The Iconoclast Our Purpose by Robert Dewart; "Building Lyndon Johnson" by David Welsh; J.O.I.N. (Jobs or Income Now) newsletters and article, "Interracial Economic Organizing in Philadelphia"
- Fellowship. The Magazine of the Fellowship of Reconciliation 1964-1966 (Box 1)
- The Institute for Policy Studies "Problems and Prospects of the New South: A Seminar Series for Congressional Assistants" 1966 Apr-Jun (Box 1)
- K-L (general) 1965-1979, n.d. (Box 1)
  including: economic development in Kentucky; "The case of the Knoxville College Students"; Civil Disorders in Louisville, Kentucky; League For Industrial Democracy news bulletin (1966) and articles, "The Roots of the Dominican Crisis" by Theodore Draper (1965) and "On the Nature of Communism and Relations with Communists"; Libertarian(1968 May); LUCHA Christian Response to Military Repression in Latin America(1978-1979)
- Letter from China by Anna Louise Strong 1966-1967 (Box 2)
- Lists of Literature Available from various organizations 1967-1968 (Box 2)
- Minority of One 1966 (Box 2)
- Mississippi Material 1963-1966, n.d. (Box 2)
- N-P (general) 1964-1967, n.d. (Box 2)
  including: "Position Paper on the Native American and Chicano Questions"; New Individualist Review(1966); "Moscow Trials in New Orleans"; The New Republic(1966 Apr); New South(1966 Winter); Other Scenes(1967); Paredon Records catalog, etc.; Peace Corps National Advisory Council; Walking Tall A Brief Sketch of Penn School, Forerunner of Penn Community Services, Frogmore, South Carolina by Edith M. Dabbs; Poverty by Sargent Shriver
- The Nation 1968-1969 (Box 2)
- National Student Association Conference -- The Administration of Southern Justice, Oberlin College 1966 Apr 28-30 (Box 2)
- "A New Left Manifesto" by Paul Booth and Edward Greer 1968 Jan 28 (Box 2)
- News Notes of the Central Committee for Conscientious Objectors 1966-1967 (Box 2)
- New clippings, chiefly about the SDS 1967, 1969 (Box 2)
- R-Z (general) 1964-1969, n.d. (Box 2)
  including: The Rap; "Some Facts about Repression"; articles about schools, "Electronics & the Psychic Drop-Out" by Marshall McLuhan and "Schools and Segregation"; Socialist Party; the South in "From the First Reconstruction to the Second" by C. Vann Woodward; South Africa; the Southern Conference Educational Fund; "The Southern Mystique" by Howard Zinn; SSRP Newsletter (Southern Rural Research Project); Southern States Industrial Council "The Unionization of the South"; articles about students; "Urban Policy in the Rationalized Society" by Donald N. Michael; articles and material about the Vietnam War; Virginia Students' Civil Rights Committee; Watts Hospital Chapter of Local 77; Young Socialist article: The Attempt to Restore Stalin
- Radical Education Project 1966-1967 (Box 2)
  including: "Contemptuous Hairdressers - Ceremonies of Humiliation in School" by Edgar Z. Friedenberg; "Medical Ghettos" by Anselm L. Strauss; "The U.A.W. settles with Ford - Sellout and Insurgency in the Auto Industry" by Jim Jacobs; "Corporate Imperialism for the Poor" by Richard Cloward and Frances Fox Piven; "The Great Flint Sit-Down Strike Against G.M. 1936-1937" by Walter Linder; "Socialist Man and the Chinese Revolution The Basis of the Cultural Revolution" by Donald McKelvey; "Wildcat: Anatomy of a Work Stoppage" by Steve Fox; "Power in American Society" by Jim Jacobs; "A Seminar On Radicalism in American History" by Ken Walzer and Dennis Gregg; "Black Liberation" by Earl Ofari; "The Contradiction of Advanced Capitalist Society and its Resolution" by Martin Nicolaus; "In a Crisis The Center Falls Out: The Role of the Faculty in The Columbia Strike" by Dick Greeman; and "Democracy and the University" by Richard K. Pope
- Southern Regional Council Special Reports 1965-1966, n.d. (Box 3)
- Southern Student Organizing Committee 1965-1968, n.d. (Box 3)
- Southern Student Organizing Committee -- Articles ca. 1965-1968, 4 folders (Box 3)
  concerning: civil rights, racism, the Vietnam War, high school reform, the decay of cities, educational issues, student power movements, radicalism, Latin America, student social action, DOW Chemical Corporation, the new left, the draft, the Selective Service System, American imperialism, Nashville power structure, nonviolence, the Democratic Party, labor in the South, women's liberation, "poor whites," and revolution
- Students for a Democratic Society 1964-1969, n.d. (Box 3)
- Students for a Democratic Society -- Articles ca. 196301968, 3 folders (Box 4)
  concerning: the Columbia University rebellion, introduction to the SDS, perspective of U.S. history, Cuba, imperialism, Huey Newton, cultural revolution in China, U.S. foreign relations, high school reform, students and labor, leadership, the War on Poverty, Dixiecrats, Appalachia, the Vietnam War, bibliographies, community organizing, poverty, eastern Kentucky, working class, the Brazil coup, civil rights, the South, Barry Goldwater, strikes, economic development, and the freedom movement in Massachusetts
- Student Union for Peace Action (SUPA) Articles 1962-1966 (Box 4)
  including an organizing manual, U.S. colonialism in Canada, power structures, education & political values, social change and the international system, developing countries, U.S. relations with China, and ideology and revolution
- The Toledo Free Press n.d. (Box 4)
- "Towards a Theory of Social Change in America" by David Gilbert, Robert Gottlieb, and Gerry Tenney 1967 Jan 23 (Box 4)
- University Christian Movement The Second Look 1967 (Box 4)
- Virginia Students' Civil Rights Committee 1966, n.d. (Box 4)
- NEWSPAPERS
  - SDS New Left Notes/SDS FIRE! 1966-1969 (Oversize S-36)
    1966 Apr / SDS New Left Notes/ Vol. 1, #11-15 / (5 newspapers)
    1966 May-Jul / SDS New Left Notes/ Vol. 1, #17-24 / (8 newspapers)
    1966 Jul / SDS New Left Notes/ Vol. 1, #26-27 / (1 newspaper)
    1966 Aug / SDS New Left Notes/ Vol. 1, #29 / (1 newspaper)
    1966 Aug-Dec / SDS New Left Notes/ Vol. 1, #31-49,There are two distinct issues of #42 and 49 / (19 newspapers)
    1967 Jan / SDS New Left Notes/ Vol. 2, #1-2 / (2 newspapers)
    1969 Jan / SDS New Left Notes/ Vol. 4, #3 / (1 newspaper)
    1969 Feb / SDS New Left Notes/ Vol. 4, #8 / (1 newspaper)
    [1969] Mar / SDS New Left Notes/ Vol. 4, #10-11 / (2 newspapers)
    1969 Apr-May / SDS New Left Notes/ Vol. 4, #15-18 / (4 newspapers)
    1969 Jun-Jul / SDS New Left Notes/ Vol. 4, #21-25 / (5 newspapers)
    1969 Aug / SDS New Left Notes/ Vol. 4, #29 / (1 newspaper)
    1969 Oct / SDS New Left Notes/ Vol. 4, #31 / (1 newspaper)
    1969 Nov-Dec / SDS New Left Notes/ Vol. 5, #5-7 / (3 newspapers)
    1969 Oct 21 / SDS New Left Notes - FIRE!/ Vol. 4, #32 / (1 newspaper) 1969 Nov / SDS FIRE!/ Vol. 1. #1-2 / (2 newspapers)
  - Miscellaneous Newspapers (A-M) (Oversize S-37)
    1966 July / Anti-Apartheid News/ (1 newspaper)
    1966 Sep - 67 Feb / Anti-Apartheid News/ (5 newspapers)
    1965 Dec - 66 May / Campus Dialogue/ Vol. 1, #1-8 / (8 newspapers)
    1966 Apr / Challenge/ Vol. II, #20 / (1 newspaper)
    1969 Feb / Connections/ Vol. III, #6 / (1 newspaper)
    [n.d.] / Counterpoint/ Vol. 2, #5-6 / (2 newspapers)
    [1967?] Mar / The East Village Other/ Vol. 2, #7 / (1 newspaper)
    [n.d.] / Free Student/ #1 / (1 newspaper)
    1966 Apr / Free Student/ #7 / (1 newspaper)
    1964 Sep / The Independent/ #147 / (1 newspaper)
    [n.d.] / Liberation, USA/ #1 / (1 newspaper)
    1967 Mar / Los Angeles Free Press/ Vol. 4, #9, issue #147 / (1 newspaper)
    1968 Dec / MDS Newsletter/ Vol. 2, #12 / (1 newspaper)
    1967 Feb / The Movement/ Vol. 3, #2 / (1 newspaper)
  - Miscellaneous Newspapers (N-W) (Oversize S-38)
    1966 Jun / new america/ Vol. V, #21-22 / (2 newspapers)
    1968 Nov / Old Mole/ Vol. 1, #4 / (1 newspaper)
    1969 Jan / Old Mole/ #6 / (1 newspaper)
    [1969?] Mar-Apr / Old Mole/ #9-10 / (2 newspapers)
    [1969?] Jun-Jul / Old Mole/ #16 / (1 newspaper)
    1969 May / protean/RADiSH/ (1 newspaper)
    1968 Dec / The Rag/ Vol III, #8 / (1 newspaper)
    [1969?] / Revolutionary Youth Movement/ (1 newspaper)
    [n.d.] / Rights of Man/ Vol. 1, #1 / (1 newspaper)
    1966 May / The Southern Patriot/ Vol. 24, #5-6 / (2 newspapers)
    1964 May / Southern School News, a supplementary publication marking a decade since the school desegregation decision of May 17, 1954 / (1 newspaper)
    [1968?] / Tennessee Teamster Times/ (1 newspaper)
    1967 Jul-Aug / Vietnam Summer News/ Vol. 1, #3-6 / (4 newspapers)
    1966 Nov / The Village Voice, pages 21-22 / (1 newspaper)
    1966 May / WIND AND CHAFF/ Vol. III, #4 / (1 newspaper)